Who was it then?
Sebenarnya siapa?
Who killed the second mother in the bathroom?
Siapa yang membunuh Bibi ke-2 di kamar mandi?
Actually,
Sebenarnya,
if we think from Xu Yazhi's perspective,
jika kita berpikir dari sudut pandang Seo A-ji,
we can find the answer.
kita bisa mendapatkan jawabannya.
First,
Pertama-tama,
the strong Lu Jingtai and Lu Jingjiang
Lu Jingtai dan Lu Jingjiang yang kuat
were definitely not her targets.
pasti bukan targetnya.
And although Tian Shan, also being a woman,
Dan Tian Shan yang juga seorang wanita,
was a good target,
meskipun merupakan tujuan yang bagus,
she couldn't determine which order Tian Shan would go to the bathroom.
tapi dia tidak bisa memastikan
If someone else entered the bathroom before her,
Jika seseorang masuk ke kamar mandi sebelum itu,
it would be troublesome.
itu akan merepotkan.
Her real target
Tujuan sebenarnya
could only be the first person to enter the bathroom.
adalah orang pertama yang masuk ke kamar mandi.
That would be you, Uncle.
yaitu Paman.
Mr. Lu Tianci,
Tuan Lu Tianci.
that's quite a good deduction.
Ini benar-benar sebuah kesimpulan yang bagus.
But I have to ask you,
Tapi aku ingin bertanya lagi.
why would the first person to enter the bathroom
orang pertama yang masuk ke kamar mandi
be me?
Kenapa aku?
Because you're the elder, of course.
Karena Anda adalah senior.
In the Lu family's customs,
Dalam aturan Keluarga Lu,
elders always have priority.
orang tua selalu diutamakan.
Xu Yazhi observed over the past few days
[Setelah observasi selama beberapa hari,]
and knew that when you were bathing,
Aku tahu saat kau mandi,
you would definitely leave bodyguard Anderson
pasti akan meninggalkan pengawal Anderson
in the room to watch everyone.
di dalam kamar untuk mengawasi semua orang.
So,
Jadi,
she wouldn't worry about being discovered when she went out.
dia tidak akan takut ketahuan.
I think Ms. Xu Yazhi must have believed
Aku pikir Nyonya Xu Yazhi pasti mengira
that Mr. Lu Tianci was old
Tuan Lu Tianci sudah tua,
and not very mobile, making him an easy target.
tidak leluasa bergerak, jadi mudah bertindak.
But what she didn't expect was
Tapi yang tidak dia sangka adalah
that Mr. Lu Tianci was actually a martial arts expert.
Tuan Lu Tianci adalah ahli seni bela diri.
When Xu Yazhi raised the knife to attack Uncle,
Saat itu, Xu Ya Zhi memegang pisau dan bersiap menyerang Paman.
she was caught by Uncle in the moment of attack,
Dia tertangkap saat menyerang.
and then he swiftly stabbed the knife into Xu Yazhi's chest.
[Lalu dia menusuk dadanya.]
That's right, Uncle.
Benar, Pak.
Qingtian and I are both trained fighters.
Aku dan cerah berlatih.
You shouldn't have acted in front of us.
Kau seharusnya tidak membantu kami.
I think Xu Yazhi's real purpose
Kurasa tujuan sebenarnya Seo Ah-ji
was also to fight over the distribution of the inheritance.
untuk memperebutkan pembagian warisan.
Well, if everything is as you say,
Jika semuanya seperti yang kau katakan,
then Uncle's actions should be considered self-defense.
seharusnya dia membela diri.
But why didn't he say so?
Tapi kenapa dia tidak memberitahuku?
I think Uncle
Aku merindukan Paman.
couldn't be absolutely certain
[Aku tidak yakin]
that the owner of this letter was Xu Yazhi.
pemilik surat ini adalah Seo Ah-ji.
That's why he placed the body
Itu sebabnya dia meletakkan jasadnya
in a place where it could be easily found,
di tempat yang mudah ditemukan.
as a warning to others not to act against him carelessly.
[untuk memperingatkan orang lain untuk tidak menyerangnya.]
Uncle,
Pak.
can you now tell us everything?
Bisakah kau menceritakan semuanya sekarang?
You're too naive, Gong Sun He.
Kau sangat naif, Gongsun Bangau.
Who are you?
Siapa kau?
You can call me by my codename, Tailor.
Kau bisa memanggilku penjahit.
You appear so openly,
Kau muncul begitu terang-terangan,
aren't you afraid we'll arrest you?
kau tidak takut kami menangkapmu?
On what grounds would you arrest me?
Kenapa kau menangkapku?
I haven't done anything.
Aku tidak melakukan apa pun.
I was invited here by Mr. Lu Tianyang.
Aku diundang oleh Tuan Lu Tianyang.
Now, as long as the lawyer
Sekarang asalkan pengacara
reads out the will,
membacakan wasiat,
the truth will come to light.
kebenaran akan terungkap.
Then, Lawyer Lin, please read the will quickly.
Kalau begitu, Pengacara Lin, cepat bacakan wasiatnya.
Alright.
Baik.
Then I will officially read the will.
Aku akan membacakan wasiat secara resmi.
Last Will and Testament.
Wasiat?
I, Lu Tianyang, hereby decide
Aku Lu Tianyang memutuskan
to distribute my estate among the following five individuals:
membagikan warisanku kepada lima orang berikut.
namely, my wife,
[Mereka adalah istriku.]
Xu Yazhi,
Xu Yazhi.
my eldest son Lu Jingtai,
Putra sulung Lu Jingtai.
my eldest daughter-in-law Tian Shan,
Menantu pertama, Tian Shan.
my younger son Lu Jingjiang, and Anderson.
Putra bungsu Lu Jingjiang dan Anderson.
These five individuals shall equally divide all assets under my name.
Kelima orang ini bisa membagi semua harta atas namaku.
October 25th, 1945.
25 Oktober tahun 34 Republik Tiongkok.
Testator:
Dekret.
Lu Tianyang
Pesan, Lu Tianyang.
Anderson?
Anderson.
Lawyer,
Pengacara.
are you sure you read that correctly?
Kau tidak salah baca, bukan?
That's correct.
Benar.
The last name is indeed Anderson.
Nama terakhir memang Anderson.
Moreover, Mr. Lu even wrote
Selain itu, Tuan Lu juga menuliskan tanggal lahirnya
Anderson's date of birth after his name.
di belakang nama Anderson.
This is so strange.
Aneh sekali.
Why isn't Uncle's name
Lalu kenapa di surat wasiat tidak ada paman?
Lu Tianci on the will?
nama Lu Tianci?
It's normal that his name isn't there.
Wajar jika tidak ada namanya.
Because the old man in front of you
Karena orang tua di depan kalian ini
is not your uncle.
bukan pamanmu.
He's actually a bodyguard who came
tapi untuk melindungi Anderson.
all the way from abroad
Aku mengikutinya dari luar negeri.
to protect Anderson.
pengawal yang melindunginya.
Then who is Anderson?
Lalu siapa Anderson?
He is the real Lu Tianci's
Lu Tianci yang asli.
child born to a woman abroad,
anak yang dilahirkan dengan seorang wanita di luar negeri.
which means he's Lu Tianyang's nephew
adalah keponakan Lu Tian.
and your cousin.
sepupu kalian.
Why did you come here?
Kau datang ke sini
What's your real purpose?
sebenarnya untuk apa?
Mr. Lu Tianyang was worried
Tuan Lu Tianyang khawatir
that someone among you might harm family members
di antara kalian akan ada orang yang menyerang keluarga
in order to fight for the inheritance.
demi merebut warisan.
So he asked me to secretly keep an eye on you all.
Jadi, dia memintaku untuk mengawasi kalian secara diam-diam.
If anyone tried to harm Anderson,
Jika ada yang menyerang Anderson,
I would intervene to stop them.
aku akan menghentikannya.
If that's the case,
Kalau begitu,
you were present when Xu Yazhi made her move?
kau juga ada di TKP saat Seo A-ji bertindak.
That's correct.
Benar.
Then why didn't you stop her?
Kenapa kau tidak menghentikannya?
If you had stopped her, she wouldn't have died.
Jika kau menghentikannya, dia tidak akan mati.
Why should I have stopped her?
Kenapa aku harus menghentikannya?
You...
Kau...
She was trying to kill this old man,
Yang ingin dia bunuh adalah orang tua ini,
not Anderson.
bukan Anderson.
Wait.
Tunggu.
You say this uncle in front of us is not my real uncle,
Kau bilang pria di depanmu ini bukan paman kandungku.
but why does he have an injury on his foot?
Lalu kenapa kakinya terluka?
Moreover,
Selain itu,
his handwriting
tulisan tangannya
matches the handwriting on the postcards we received.
sama dengan tulisan di kartu pos yang dikirim.
The handwriting is the same
Tulisan tangannya sama.
because this old man wrote those postcards.
Karena orang tua ini yang menulis kartu pos.
Why is that?
Lalu kenapa?
Ten years ago,
Sepuluh tahun lalu,
your uncle was outdoors
Pamanmu ada di luar.
when a tornado
Karena sebuah tornado,
caused him to lose his right arm.
kehilangan lengan kanan.
Since then,
Sejak saat itu,
all letters and postcards have been written by his good friend,
semua surat dan kartu pos
who is this old man in front of you.
[dan orang tua di hadapannya.]
These are the letters
Ini adalah surat
Lu Tianci sent to his brother over the years,
surat yang dikirim Lu Tianci kepada kakaknya.
which provide a complete account of this matter.
memiliki penjelasan yang lengkap tentang hal ini.
Six months ago,
Setengah tahun lalu,
Lu Tianci passed away abroad due to illness.
Lu Tianci meninggal karena sakit di luar negeri.
Your father also fell gravely ill.
Dan ayah kalian juga tidak bisa bangun karena sakit.
To ensure his nephew could also have a good life,
Demi keponakannya, dia bisa hidup dengan baik.
he allocated a portion of the inheritance to Anderson.
Itu sebabnya dia membagi sebagian warisannya kepada Anderson.
Then why did this old man impersonate our uncle?
Lalu kenapa pria tua itu menyamar sebagai pamanku?
Could it be
Mungkinkah
he wanted to claim this part of the inheritance for himself?
ingin mengambil semua warisan ini sebagai milik sendiri?
If he really wanted to claim the inheritance for himself,
Jika dia benar-benar ingin mengambil warisannya,
he wouldn't have become the target of an attack.
dia tidak akan diserang.
If someone knew
Jika ada yang tahu
Anderson is Lu Tianci's son.
Anderson adalah putra Lu Tianci,
Then the person who sent the threatening letter
Orang yang mengirim surat ancaman
will definitely target Anderson.
pasti akan menyerang Anderson.
That's why he impersonated Lu Tianci,
Jadi dia menyamar sebagai Lu Tianci
to make the intimidator direct their attacks towards him.
untuk membuat orang yang takut mengarahkan tombak padanya.
The best proof is
Bukti terbaik adalah
that every time he takes a shower,
setiap kali dia mandi,
he makes sure Anderson is with all of you.
Anderson bersama kalian semua
is the safest.
adalah yang paling aman.
The original intention was to catch the intimidator.
Awalnya ingin menangkap ancaman,
But he ended up accidentally killing him.
tapi dia malah membunuhnya.
Based on the circumstances at the time,
Berdasarkan situasi saat itu,
it was indeed self-defense.
itu memang pembelaan diri.
However, once he reveals this situation,
Tapi begitu dia mengatakan ini,
he will definitely have to go to the police station for questioning.
dia harus pergi ke kantor polisi untuk diinterogasi.
That's why he placed the body in the most easily discoverable location.
Itu sebabnya dia meletakkan jasadnya di tempat yang paling mudah ditemukan.
I see.
Ternyata...
So that's how it is.
Ternyata begitu.
Am I correct?
Apa aku benar?
Mr. Qin Dongli,
Tuan Qin Dongli.
you are absolutely correct.
Yang kamu katakan benar sepenuhnya.
That's exactly how it is.
Benar.
However, there's one thing I didn't know.
Tapi ada satu hal yang aku tidak tahu.
I didn't know that Mr. Lu Tianyang
Aku tidak tahu Tuan Lu Tianyang
had someone secretly protecting Anderson.
mencari orang untuk diam-diam melindungi Anderson.
If I had known,
Jika aku tahu,
I wouldn't have been so nervous
aku tidak perlu begitu gugup.
and killed in self-defense.
Serangan balik.
Xu Yazhi.
Xu Ya Zhi.
Mr. Tailor,
Tuan Penjahit.
since your task is already completed,
Karena tugasmu sudah selesai,
please come with me to the police station for investigation.
ikut aku ke kantor polisi untuk diinterogasi.
I have no interest in going to the police station.
Aku tidak tertarik ke kantor polisi.
The reason I accepted the invitation
Aku menerima undangan
was to repay Mr. Lu Tianyang's kindness.
untuk membalas budi Tuan Lu Tianyang.
If you don't want to perish together with me,
Jika kalian tidak ingin mati bersamaku,
you're welcome to arrest me.
kau bisa menangkapku.
Should we still pursue?
Haruskah kita mengejarnya?
Let it go. It's too dangerous.
Sudahlah, terlalu berbahaya.
Mr. Qin,
Tuan Qin.
please come back to the police station with us.
Ikut kami ke kantor polisi.
Don't worry.
Jangan khawatir.
Gong Sunhe is an excellent detective under my command.
Gongsun Bangau adalah inspektur yang hebat.
With him protecting Anderson's safety,
Ada dia yang melindungi keamanan Anderson,
you can be completely at ease.
kau bisa tenang.
If that's the case,
Kalau begitu,
then I'll leave it to you.
tolong jaga dia.
I just found out.
Aku baru tahu.
This Anderson doesn't speak Chinese at all.
Anderson sama sekali tidak bisa berbahasa Mandarin.
He doesn't even know that he's been here
Dia bahkan tidak tahu beberapa hari ini
waiting to inherit these past few days.
untuk membagi warisannya di sini.
What should we do?
Apa yang harus kita lakukan?
Should we take him to the police station too?
Apa aku harus membawanya ke kantor polisi?
I'll go talk to him.
Aku akan memberitahunya.
Don't worry.
Jangan khawatir.
Mr. Qin will be back soon.
Tuan Qin akan segera kembali.
Let's wait for him here, okay?
Kita tunggu dia di sini, oke?
Where is uncle going?
Paman mau ke mana?
Will he be alright?
Apa dia akan baik-baik saja?
He's going to the police station to assist with the investigation. He'll be fine.
Dia pergi ke kantor polisi untuk membantu penyelidikan, dia akan baik-baik saja.
I promise you.
Aku berjanji.
Good child,
Anak baik.
this detective will protect you.
Tuan detektif ini akan melindungimu.
I'll be back soon,
Aku akan segera kembali.
okay?
Ya?
Okay.
Baik.
Anderson,
Anderson.
your father is my uncle.
Ayahmu adalah pamanku.
We are cousins.
Kami sepupu.
We're family.
Satu keluarga.
Don't worry, cousin.
Adik Sepupu, jangan khawatir.
I'll keep you safe.
Aku akan melindungimu.